Good morning, this is Dan Margulies filling in for Rabbi Linzer
and we are starting from the last line of למד אלף עמוד
אלף. Lamed Aleph Amud Aleph. תני אבימי בריה דרבי אבהו. Tani Avimi
brei deRabbi Abbahu. So Avimi the son of Rabbi Abbahu said, יש
מאכיל לאביו פסיוני, Yesh Ma'achil l'aviv pisyoni, there are people who feed
their parents pheasants, וטורדו מן העולם, v'tardo min ha'olam, and that drags
them out of the
world, ויש מטחינו בריחים, v'yesh mat'chino b'reichayim, and there are people who
make their parents grind behind a millstone, ומביאו לחיי העולם הבא, u'mevi'o
l'chayei ha'olam ha'ba, and that brings them for עולם הבא. Olam Ha-ba.
Rabbi Linzer spoke very beautifully yesterday about how it so shows the
deep subjectivity or contextual necessity for context in understanding
the relationships involved with כיבוד אב ואם Kibbud Av Va'em and מורא
אם ואב Mora Em Va'av in a way that other מצוות mitzvot
maybe don't have the same kind of need for context. Okay. אמר
רבי אבהו, Amar Rabbi Abbahu, כגון אבימי ברי. ke-gon Avimi brei. So
I'm now going to give you example, my son Avimi, קיים מצוות
כיבוד. kiyem mitzvat kibbud. How well did he keep the מצוה mitzvah
of כיבוד? kibbud? Incredibly, it's the next best thing. So we got
the next best thing, so that worked out perfect. Okay. So אבימי
ברי, Avimi brei, that is Rabbi Abbahu is saying about Avimi his
son, קיים מצוות כיבוד. kiyem mitzvat kibbud. He did the מצוה mitzvah
of כיבוד. kibbud. How so? חמישה בני סמכי הוו ליה לאבימי בחיי
אביו. Chamisha bani samchei hava leh l'Avimi b'chayei aviv. So Avimi himself
had five sons. It's a question of how to understand בני סמכי.
benei samchei. Does בני סמכי benei samchei mean that they were already
had received סמיכה? semicha? Seems strange to think that was happening in
בבל Bavel or that they were suitable to receive סמיכה. semicha. בני
סמוכי על שולחנו? Bnei smucho al shulchano? Or it means סמוכי על
שולחנו? samucho al shulchano? Does it mean that they were just grown
children? It's not exactly so clear what it's talking about, but he
had five of some sort of children in his father's lifetime. וכי
הוה אתי רבי אבהו, ve'chi hava atei Rabbi Abbahu, and when Rabbi
Abbahu would come to visit, that is when the grandfather would show
up, the father Avimi would do what? So when Rabbi Abbahu would
come, קרי בבבא, kari babava, he would call at the doorway, רהיט
ואזיל ופתח ליה. rahit va'azil upatach leh. So Avimi, that is his
son even though he has five grown children of his own, he
would run to the door and open the door, ואמר אין אין
עד דמטאי התם. ve'amar in in ad d'matai hatam. And he would
say "Yes, yes" like "Yes, I'm coming" until he would reach the
door. That is he wouldn't let his children do כיבוד kibbud for
their grandfather, he would make sure to do it himself. One thing
I heard from Rabbi Love and Rabbi Linzer was very pleased to
hear it it seems, was just the notion that so many of
the stories about כיבוד אב ואם Kibbud Av Va'em are not about
what we normally think of
teenage children relating to their middle-aged parents. Most of the stories in
the גמרא Gemara about כיבוד אב ואם Kibbud Av Va'em are about
adult children relating to their elderly and growing elderly parents. And that's
a very different mode of relationship when you're trying to balance on
the one hand the relationship you have with your parents and also
the relationship you have with your spouse, your children, and other needs
in life. We don't know how old these people were. We don't
know how old these people were but he had... They married a
lot younger. He had five grown children. The point is he had
a household that he was responsible for. They were grown at twelve
back then. Anyway, okay, it's just important to note. You see continually
and especially on today's דף daf a number of examples which touch
on things that seem like dementia or seem like progressive decline of
elderly parents and to think about how that teaches us about מצוות
כיבוד אב ואם mitzvat Kibbud Av Va'em in a very different way.
Yeah.
תוספות Tosafot says that Rabbi Abbahu was in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
but Avimi lived in בבל. Bavel. So that's also interesting to consider
the fact that maybe he didn't get to see him so often.
So when when he would come to visit it was a big
to-do and nonetheless he reserved the right to do the מצוה mitzvah
for himself interestingly. Okay, so the next... the next case. Okay. עד
דמטאי התם. Ad d'matai hatam. יום אחד, Yom echad, אמר ליה אשקיין
מיא. amar leh ashkein maya. He said "pour me some water". The
grandfather. The grandfather asked Avimi his son pour me some water. עד
דאייתי ליה, Ad d'ayitey leh, so by the time he had gotten
to him, נמנם גחין. nimnam gachein. He was already he was already
snoring asleep. So קאי עליה עד דאיתער. kai alei ad d'it'ar. He
stood there next to him until he woke up. אסתייעא מילתא ודרש
אבימי מזמור לאסף. ista'yei miltei ve'darash Avimi Mizmor l'Asaph.
And because of this action he merited to be able to interpret
the מזמור, Mizmor, actually today's שיר של יום, shir shel yom, מזמור
לאסף, Mizmor l'Asaph, אלוהים ניצב בעדת אל. Elohim nitzav b'adat el.
So interesting to think about again the question of how much is
כיבוד אב ואם Kibbud Av Va'em related to the relationship between human
beings and God, is the relationship similar to how a person relates
to their parents. Okay. אמר ליה רבי יעקב בר אבוה לאביי כגון
אנא. Amar leh Rabbi Yaakov bar Abbuha l'Abaye: ke-gon ana. I'm going
to give you another example. And תוספות Tosafot has a long תוספות
Tosafot on מזמור לאסף אלהים באו גוים בנחלתך Mizmor l'Asaph Elohim bau
goyim b'nachalatecha which has different מזמור לאסף, Mizmor l'Asaph, it's yeah it's
an interesting
question which מזמור לאסף, Mizmor l'Asaph, anyway the ראשונים Rishonim deal with
it. Okay. So אמר ליה רבי יעקב בר אבוה... amar leh Rabbi
Yaakov bar Abbuha... בר אבוה, bar Abbuha, interesting his name is בר
אבוה, bar Abbuha, the son of his father. Father, you know you
always wonder when you see somebody named אבא Abba in the גמרא
Gemara was the name actually אבא Abba or was it just that
they had the same name and since you can't call your parent's
name, they would use אבא Abba as a substitute. But anyway, so
רבי יעקב בר אבוה לאביי Rabbi Yaakov bar Abuha l'Abaye כגון אנא
דעד דאתינא
מבי רב ke-gon ana de-ad de-atina mi-be Rav when I would get
back from yeshiva, so אבא מדלי ליה כסא Abba madli lei kasa
my father would pour me a glass of wine, ואימא מזגא לי
ve-ima mazga li and my mother would mix the wine with the
water. So היכי אעביד heichi e-avid what should I do? That is,
his parents are being deferential to him. They each prepared a glass
of wine for him, and now he wants to know what should
I do. So he asks, so אמר ליה amar lei מאימך קבל
me-imecha kabel you should receive it from your mother, ומאבוך לא תקבל
u-me-avucha lo tikabel don't receive it from your father דכיון דבר תורה
הוא de-keivan de-bar Torah hu because your father himself is a בן
תורה ben Torah that is, he's a learned man. So חלשא דעתיה
chalsha datei he'll be more hurt by you, the son, accepting the
drink from him. Now, it's very strange, this is a... couldn't he
take both? Couldn't... isn't this kind of a strange role reversal? It's
like by not accepting it, he's offending him. Right, it's strange to
think, but again, what number of layers are going on in this
story? This is parents treating their son the way we're meant to
think that the children should be treating their parents. And this is
also how much does it play in that he's a תלמיד חכם
talmid chacham and how their respect and honor for him as a
תלמיד חכם talmid chacham is playing into their familial relationship. So there's
a lot to unpack there. I mean, each of these different stories
you could spend, you know, a long time analyzing psychologically and with
ראשונים Rishonim and all sorts of things. Okay, דכיון דבר תורה הוא
חלשא דעתיה. de-keivan de-bar Torah hu chalsha datei. רבי טרפון הוה ליה
ההיא אימא. Rabbi Tarfon hava lei ha-hee ima. דכל אימת דהוה בעי
למיסק לפוריא גחין וסליק ליה. de-chol eimat de-hava baei lemisik le-purya gachin
ve-salik lei.
So when רבי טרפון's Rabbi Tarfon's mother needed to get into bed,
so he would lie down and she would step up on him.
וכל אימת דהוה נחית נחתא עילויה. ve-chol eimat de-hava nachit nachita ilu-ei.
And whenever she would come down from the bed, she would step
down on him. So I guess she was very frail or she
wasn't able to climb up into the bed or climb down from
the bed herself, so she needed רבי טרפון's Rabbi Tarfon's help and
רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon would lie down on the ground in order
to be a step stool for his mother. So אתא וקמשתבח ביה
במדרשא. ata ve-ka-mishtabach bei be-midrasha. When רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon came to
the בית מדרש beis midrash and he was kind of bragging about
how well he had done the מצוה mitzvah of כיבוד אב ואם,
kibbud av va-em, כיבוד אם kibbud em in this case, so אמרו
ליה amru lei עדיין לא הגעת לחצי כיבוד. adayin lo higata le-chatzi
kibbud. You haven't even reached half of what כיבוד kibbud is. כלום
זרקה ארנקי בפניך לים ולא הכלמתה? klum zarka arneki be-fanecha le-yam ve-lo
hichlamta?
Have you reached the point where if she would throw your wallet
into the ocean in front of you that you would not get
upset at her, you would not be angry at her? So this
raises major questions for the פוסקים poskim about how much money or
how much personal embarrassment does a person have to suffer in order
to fulfill the מצוה mitzvah of כיבוד אב ואם. kibbud av va-em.
Those are two separate questions, and in this case, it's part of
unpacking what's the role of the wallet in the story. Is it
throwing your wallet away just because it's a הפסד ממון, hefsed mammon,
you're losing the money in the wallet, or is it very embarrassing
that you let your parents treat you in this way in public?
Again, thinking about how is it parents embarrass their children in public,
how is it that children often embarrass their parents in public. What
does even embarrassing you mean in public?
Well, that's how רש"י Rashi I think makes it into a question
of embarrassment. No, ולא הכלמתה ve-lo hichlamta is like, you know, it's
not like constantly people... Right,
but it comes up later as well. רב יוסף כי הוה שמע
קל כרעא דאימיה Rav Yosef ki hava shama kal kara de-imeih אמר
איקום מקמי שכינה דאתיא. amar ekum mikamei Shechina de-asya.
So when רב יוסף Rav Yosef would hear his mother coming, he
said, I'm going to get up to greet the שכינה Shechina who
is coming by. He was very deferential. אמר רבי יוחנן אשרי מי
שלא חמאן. amar Rabbi Yochanan ashrei mi she-lo chamman. So רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan כי עברתיה אימיה ki ibartih imeih מית אביו. meis aviv.
I'm sorry, what did he say? Sorry I'm sorry I got mixed
up a little bit. רש"י... Rashi...
So what does this word mean? I forgot now. חמאן? chamman? Where
are you? So רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. רבי יוחנן אשרי מי שלא
חמאן. Rabbi Yochanan ashrei mi she-lo chamman. רש"י Rashi explains it but
I don't know what the word means. Maybe gets angry? I think
so, but now... right, okay. Yeah, I got a little bit mixed
up. Okay. So is it from אכמיא? echmaya? Something like that. It's
almost better not to see them because then you're never... right. Right.
Right. Koren translates as saw.
Yeah, exactly. Right, like in חמיא חמיא. chamya chamya. In other words,
better not to have seen them, maybe because it's
just
an ironic way of saying it since I can never
do what I need to do, it's almost better not to see
them. Right. Okay. So רבי יוחנן כי עברתיה אימיה מית אביו כי
ילדתיה מיתה אימיה. Rabbi Yochanan ki ibartih imeih meis aviv ki yeladtih
misa imeih. I know it sounds like, you know, see your parents...
right, as if to say that you should never have even seen
that your parents
pass away. You'll never be able to properly fulfill the מצוה. mitzvah.
Right, but doesn't that make something the bar... But isn't that making
the bar so high that... well, that's that's the other voice in
this, right. Wait, sorry. No, then they explained רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
כי עברתה אימיה מית אבוה ki ivarta imeh met avuh when רבי
יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan mother was, meaning like he when she was pregnant
with him his father died and then as soon as he was
born she died. Right, and אביי. Abaye. So he never had the
opportunity.
Right. At least he never had to... right. He was orphaned his
whole life for them to be able to... it's good because he
never failed. Right, he never failed at כיבוד אב ואם. Kibbud Av
v'Eim. That almost feels like a psychological justification for making such a
statement, you know? Right, meaning it's for his own life. Right. And
again, the question of do you see, do you see the מצוה
mitzvah as an opportunity or do you see the מצוה mitzvah as
something which has such a high bar that you're unable to live
up to it? So דהכי אמרינן de-hakhi amrinan רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
כי עברתה אימיה, ki ivarta imeh, so when his mother became pregnant,
מת אביו, met aviv, יולדתו מתה אמו. yoladeto metah imo. And when
she gave birth then his mother died. וכן אביי, V'khen Abaye, and
אביי Abaye also. So interestingly a trope of this kind of orphaning
of great אמוראים Amora'im almost suggesting that they became great because they
lived under such difficult circumstances, but also it enabled them to not
have failed at כיבוד אב ואם. Kibbud Av v'Eim. So איני והאמר
אביי אמרה לי אם, eyni ve-ha-amar Abaye amra li em, ההיא אמר
בניתאי הוי... hahi amar bnitei havae... Right.
אמרה לי, amra li, right. So אביי Abaye always references his mother.
So no, ההיא אמר בניתאי הוי. hahi amar bnitei havae. That was
his nurse, his adoptive mother that raised him throughout his life.
Right. And again the question of how do we consider adoptive parents
in הלכה halacha is an important and sensitive issue, but obviously there
are a lot of פוסקים poskim who really do consider the relationship
between an adoptive parent to be of great significance, obviously. Even the
notion of מלמדו תורה melamdo Torah is כמגדלו, k'megadlo, that teaching a
student תורה Torah and obviously raising someone as your own child is
equivalent in many ways to actually having raised your own child and
is of great significance. Okay. רב אסי הוה ליה ההיא אמא זקנה.
Rav Asi hava leh hahi ima zkeina. He had, רב אסי Rav
Asi had an old mother. אמרה ליה בעינא תכשיטין. amra leh baina
tachshitin. She said, I want jewelry. עבד לה בעינא גברא אנחל לה
בעינא גברא דשפיר כותיך. avad lah baina gavra anal lah baina gavra
de-shapir k'vatekh. So שבקה ואזל לארץ
ישראל. shavka v'azal l'Eretz Yisrael. So
basically he got very frustrated with his mother's request and eventually he
just decided I'm going to go to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Okay.
So שמע דקא אזלא אבתריה. shama de-ka azla abatreh. Wait, did he
ask for sure, or did he maybe go to ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael to find her a husband?
It sounds like he went to run
away, at least from how I would read the story.
Perhaps you read it the other way. I don't know, right. But
okay. So שמע דקא אזלא אבתריה, shama de-ka azla abatreh,
so he heard that she followed him. So אתא לקמיה דרבי יוחנן.
ata l'kamei de-Rabbi Yochanan. He went to רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. אמר
ליה מהו לצאת מארץ לחוצה לארץ? amar leh mahu l'tzeit me-Eretz l'chutz
la-Aretz? Am I allowed to leave ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael in order
to go to חוץ לארץ chutz la-Aretz to escape my mother? אמר
ליה אסור. amar leh asur. לקראת
אמא מהו? likrat ima mahu? What if I'm going to go visit
my mother? אמר ליה איני יודע. amar leh eyni yodeia. Right, meaning
he is trying to escape his mother, but he's asking the question,
are you allowed to leave ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to go to
חוץ לארץ? chutz la-Aretz? Answer, no. Question number two, am I allowed
to leave ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to go to חוץ לארץ chutz
la-Aretz to visit my mother? And he says איני יודע. eyni yodeia.
As if to say רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan already somehow knew something
was fishy with the story.
It's an interesting question of again how to unpack a lot of
what's going on here, but obviously this is רב אסי Rav Asi
seemingly having a lot of difficulty relating to his mother as she
got as she got older. Okay. So אירכס פורתא irtach purta הדר
אתא אמר ליה אסי נתבצצסיה. hadar ata amar leh Asi nitvatzisaseih. This
is the same רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan who was grateful not to
have parents. Yes. So that's also the point, right. And again, each
of their characters are coming in together. So he says now the
point that רב אסי Rav Asi is worried his... so אמר ליה
אסי נתבצצסיה. amar leh Asi nitvatzisaseih. He said, אסי, Asi, you want
to leave. So המקום יחזירך לשלום. Ha-Makom yachzirekha l'shalom. Then God should
protect you on your journey back.
אתא לקמיה דרבי אלעזר ata l'kamei de-Rabbi Elazar אמר ליה חס ושלום.
amar leh chas v'shalom. No, you should never leave. דילמא מירתח רתח.
dilma mirtach rattach. Maybe maybe she's going to get angry at you,
or maybe God is going to get angry at you, or maybe
you're going to get angry at רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. Look, רש"י
Rashi says that חס ושלום מירתח רתח עלי רבי יוחנן. chas v'shalom
mirtach rattach alay Rabbi Yochanan. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is going to
be angry at me, רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, if I פוסק paskin
against him. So even though I might support you in this situation,
again רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan doesn't know what it's like to deal
in this situation. Well, maybe רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan will be angry
at you, or he'll be angry at me for really wanting to
leave. So you know, he said, alright fine, you can go. Right.
So there are two different ways to read who he's angry at.
So אמר ליה, amar leh, so מאי אמר לך? mai amar lakh?
אמר ליה המקום יחזירך לשלום. amar leh Ha-Makom yachzirekha l'shalom. So he
said God should protect you on your journey home. So אמר ליה
ואם איתא דרתח לא המברך לך. amar leh v'im ata de-rattach lo
hamvarkh lakh. If he was going to get angry at you, he
wouldn't have given you such a ברכה. berakha. So
אדהכי והכי שמע לארונא דקא אתי. ade-hachi v'hachi shama l'arona de-ka atei.
sort of got the sense that he should be going. Okay. אמר
אי ארונא. amar i aruna. Is it here he says like his
mother's coffin? His mother's coffin. His mother's coffin. Yeah. Because at that
point he heard so what happened by the time he had figured
out that he was going to go back and see her, she
had already died. You mean see her, he knew that she was
in Eretz... No, but she, right, so she was coming to Eretz
Yisrael and he thought that she was just chasing after him to
bother him. And then by the time he had decided, okay, now
I'm going to go to Bavel, which was running away from her
or was going back to her depending on whether she had come
to Eretz Yisrael or not, it was too late. Okay. So אמר
אי ידעי לא נפקי. amar i yadai lo nafki. If I had
known, I would not have left. Meaning, if I had known that
my mother's life was coming to an end, I wouldn't have left
her alone in Bavel for her to have to fend for herself.
It's interesting also to note that she was already in the coffin
and being brought to be buried by the time he encountered her.
That is, somebody else took care of the burial, presumably the rest
of his family was still in Bavel. So it's interesting to
consider what kind... now he feels a deep guilt about not having
been involved in her burial either. Okay. תנו רבנן מכבדו בחייו ומכבדו
במותו. tanu rabanan mechabdo be-chayav u-mechabdo be-moto. You have an obligation of
כיבוד kibbud for parents both in their lifetime and after their death.
בחייו כיצד? be-chayav keitzad? How you keep כבוד kavod in their lifetime?
הנשמע בדבר אביו למקום לא יאמר שלחוני בשביל עצמי מהרוני בשביל עצמי
פטרוני בשביל עצמי. ha-nishma bi-dvar aviv la-makom lo yomar shalchuni bi-shvil atzmi
maharuni bi-shvil atzmi patruni bi-shvil atzmi. So if you're in a... if
you have to go do something, you can't say, let me go,
send me along so I can go for myself or speed me
along so I can go for myself, let me do it for
myself, אלא כולהו בשביל אבא. ela kulhu bi-shvil abba.
Everything is for, for my parent or for my father. במותו כיצד?
bi-moto keitzad?
In his death, how do you honor him? האומר דבר שמועה מפיו
לא יאמר כך אמר אבא אלא כך אמר אבא מרי הריני כפרת
משכבו. ha-omer davar shmuah mi-piv lo yomar kach amar abba ela kach
amar abba mori ha-reini kaparat mishkavo. You can't say, this is what
my father
said, but this is what my father, my teacher said, for whom
I am the atonement for his משכב, mishkav, his lying down, that
is his, his burial, his grave. Do people really actually have to
say that? Okay, so he says והני מילי תוך שנים עשר חודש.
ve-hanei milei toch shneim asar chodesh. That's only in the first twelve
months. מכאן ואילך אומר זכרונו לברכה לחיי העולם הבא. mikan va-eilach omer
zichrono l'vracha l'chayei ha-olam ha-ba.
Afterwards you say זכרונו לברכה. zichrono l'vracha. So the first twelve months,
there's a notion that the child provides כפרה kaparah for their parents,
deceased parents, and so throughout those twelve months whenever you're thinking of
your parents, whenever you mention your parents, you're supposed to mention the
notion of הריני כפרת משכבו. ha-reini kaparat mishkavo.
And I've heard some people who are מקפיד makpid about that and
often not so מקפיד makpid again. Parents may also have expressed wishes
about how they want to be remembered after they pass on and
that כבוד kavod applies as well. Yeah, but is there really a
notion that you should be taking upon yourself you know like someone
else's punishment? But it's not. It says הריני כפרת משכבו. ha-reini kaparat
mishkavo. It's unclear what הריני כפרת משכבו ha-reini kaparat mishkavo means, presumably
at least it's become associated with our notion of saying קדיש kaddish
and and going to מנין minyan regularly after a parent passes away
in order to pray on their behalf and to somehow speed them
along in their post-mortem
something, whatever it is, גיהנום Gehinnom or or into עולם הבא. Olam
Ha-Ba. Well, it's the way to look at it, there's two ways
of approaching it, one is like, okay you know, do whatever I
can to improve their עולם הבא Olam Ha-Ba by doing זכויות, zechuyot,
but there's another way is the negative, in other words, all evil
will fall me as... so רש"י. Rashi. But as he's right, all
evil due to them befall me, like that's... right, but the phrase
כפרת משכבו kaparat mishkavo is is intentionally ambiguous. It means in some
way how I live my life is beneficial for my deceased parents.
Exactly. But the way רש"י, Rashi, well רש"י Rashi has a very
heavy notion. I mean again, thinking about you know so many of
the pietistic practices from חסידי אשכנז Chasidei Ashkenaz trickle into אשכנזי Ashkenazi
הלכה halacha based on after you know all mourning practices, a lot
of that comes through that that stream. So it could also be
on the positive. It could also be positive, right, everything good that
you do now is לעילוי נשמת, le-ilui nishmat, that's what כפרת משכבו
kaparat mishkavo is. Right. Okay. תנו רבנן חכם משנה שם אביו ושם
רבו. tanu rabanan chacham meshaneh shem aviv ve-shem rabo. So when a
person is a חכם, chacham, he's a rabbi teaching a שיעור shiur
or something, you have when you're quoting something from your parent or
from your teacher, you have to change their name. That is, you
have to say not just, you know,
Rabbi so-and-so, but you have to say, my רבי rebbe said such
and such. Okay. תורגמן אינו משנה. turgaman eino meshaneh. But the תורגמן
turgaman again, the תורגמן turgaman is the one who sits next to
the person teaching the שיעור shiur and says it over again louder
and clearer and better explained, gives a חזרה שיעור, chazarah shiur, something
like that. So the תורגמן turgaman does not have to change the
name. Because if... presumably it's not so the גמרא Gemara has to
ask. So לא שם אביו ולא שם רבו. lo shem aviv ve-lo
shem rabo. So אבוה דמאן? avuha de-man? Whose father are they talking
about? אילימא אבוה דתורגמן? ilima avuha de-turgaman? If it's the תורגמן's turgaman
father, אטו תורגמן לאו בר חיובא הוא? atu turgaman lav bar chiyuva
hu? So what, you're telling me that a תורגמן turgaman is somehow
exempt from showing כבוד kavod for for his parents? אלא אמר רבא
שם אביו של חכם ושם רבו של חכם. ela amar Rava shem
aviv shel chacham ve-shem rabo shel chacham. No, it's the teacher of
the חכם chacham or the parent of the חכם. chacham. of the
חכם. chacham. And therefore that's why the חכם chacham has to change
it, but the תורגמן Turgeman doesn't have that relationship. Presumably also the
clarity of the presentation from the תורגמן Turgeman is also necessary. That
is, for the תורגמן, Turgeman, the goal is clarity. And so it's
also a sense of that's maybe the הוה אמינא, hava amina, which
is rejected. כי הא דאמר רב אשי, Ki ha de-amar Rav Ashi,
כי הוה דרש בפרקא, ki hava darash be-pirka, איהו אמר אבא מארי.
ihu amar Abba Mari. So he was teaching the שיעור shiur and
he would say אבא מארי. Abba Mari. ואמרי, Ve-amrei, אמר הכי אמר
רב אשי. amar hachi amar Rav Ashi. So when the תורגמן Turgeman
would repeat it, he would say this is what רב אשי Rav
Ashi said. So that's what מר בר רב אשי, Mar bar Rav
Ashi, when מר בר רב אשי Mar bar Rav Ashi would teach,
he would just say אבא מארי Abba Mari and the תורגמן Turgeman
would repeat it over like that. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, איזו מורא
ואיזו כיבוד? eizu mora ve-eizu kibbud? What's the difference between מורא mora
and כיבוד? kibbud? These are two separate מצוות, mitzvot, so what are
their parameters? מורא, Mora, לא עומד במקומו, lo omed bimkomo, don't stand
in his place, ולא יושב במקומו, velo yoshev bimkomo, and do not
sit in his place, ולא סותר דבריו, velo soter devarav, do not
contradict him or do not סותר, soter, destroy his words. It's an
interesting formulation. ולא מכריעו, Velo machrio, okay, and don't contradict.
כיבוד, Kibbud, מאכיל ומשקה מלביש ומכסה. ma'achil umashkeh malbish umachaseh. And the
obligations of כיבוד kibbud are providing food, providing drink, מלביש malbish clothing,
ומכסה umachaseh presumably pajamas or heat in the wintertime depending in some
sense the same kind of requirement. So similar to מלביש. malbish. מלביש
Malbish is what you wear during the day, מכסה machaseh is what
you wear at night. מכניס ומוציא, Machnis umotzi, and also transportation, that
is, bringing them to where they need to go, מוציא motzi bringing
them back. Okay, איבעיא להו, ibaiya lehu, משל מי? mishel mi? So
whose money has to pay for this? That is, fine, the children
have the responsibility to perform all of these actions for their parents.
They have to provide that they have food and that they have
something to drink and have clothes to wear, but whose money pays
for it? Charlie, you have a
question? Ah, okay, so that's an interesting and important question as well.
That is, in a הלכה halakhic debate, we saw what, yesterday or
two days ago, right, והב בסופה, Vahev be-Sufa, the whole significance of
in תלמוד תורה, Talmud Torah, we have lower level of concern about
people's honor and people's respect because of the, we're all looking for
the truth, we're all fighting for what we believe is correct. So
that's a situation where there's less כבוד. kavod. But in real life,
but because אין כבוד אלא תורה, ein kavod ella Torah, so the
תורה Torah itself represents the כבוד kavod that we're trying to show
and that different kind of discourse characterizes the הלכה halakhic debate. I
would say very differently than a normal day-to-day life where you obviously
would have to have much more a deferential relationship. And there have
been a lot of ספרים sefarim written about כיבוד אב ואם kibbud
av va-em that take a very, I would say, traditionalist approach, that
is, taking from the גמרא Gemara and just sort of understanding things
very literally. And there are a lot of books that have also
tried to make clear how to apply these הלכות halakhot in situations
that maybe our parents aren't מקפיד makpid about which seat at the
dining room table they sit at, but there are other things that
they are more מקפיד makpid about and to think about how, how
even if the גמרא Gemara says, okay, what's
מורא? mora? עומד במקומו, Omed bimkomo, יושב במקומו, yoshev bimkomo, if I
know my father is not going to be upset by that or
my mother is not going to be upset by that but I
know something else that will bother them very deeply, maybe there is
also room to reconsider. Is it very formal and technical in this
way or does it really mean to bring about that emotional and
relational state of מורא mora and כבוד? kavod? So those are really
major הלכה halakhic questions. Okay, so fine. So איבעיא להו, ibaiya lehu,
משל מי? mishel mi? Whose money? רב יהודה אמר משל בן. Rav
Yehuda amar mishel ben. It has to be from the child's possessions.
רב נתן בר אושעיא אמר משל אב. Rav Natan bar Oshaya amar
mishel av. רב
נתן בר אושעיא Rav Natan bar Oshaya says it has to be
the parent's money. That is, they have to save for retirement. But
once they're not able to manage their own affairs, the children have
to administer the money appropriately to provide all of the necessities for
their parents. So that's like the notion of a retirement account. אמרו
ליה רבנן לרבי ירמיה, Amru lei rabanan le-Rabbi Yirmiyah, ואמרי לה, ve-amrei
lah, לבריה דרבי ירמיה, le-brei de-Rabbi Yirmiyah, כמאן דאמר משל אב. ke-man
de-amar mishel av. So they taught over this whole סוגיא sugya and
they פסקןed pasken that it was משל אב. mishel av. That is,
the parent's property pays for this obligation. מתיבי, Metivei, נאמר כבד את
אביך ואת אמך. ne'emar kabbed et avicha ve'et imecha. The פסוק pasuk
says you have to honor your parents. ונאמר כבד את ה' מהונך,
Ve-ne'emar kabbed et Adonai mehoncha, just like the comparison we had already,
the פסוק pasuk from משלי, Mishlei, you have to show כבוד kavod
to God as well. מה להלן בחסרון כיס, Mah le-hallan be-chisron kis,
just like the כבוד kavod for God has to be חסרון כיס,
chisron kis, you have to lose money, אף כאן בחסרון כיס. af
kan be-chisron kis. So here too you have to lose the money.
ואי אמרת משל אב, Ve-i amrat mishel av, מאי נפקא ליה מיניה?
mai nafka lei minei? לביטול מלאכה. Le-bittul melacha. No, it's not about
actually spending your own money, it's about ביטול מלאכה. bittul melacha. That
is, taking time off of work to care for your parents. So
this is a very different notion of חסרון כיס. chisron kis. It's
not I have to go and spend the money for x, y,
and z; it's that I have to take time off of work
and that the amount of money I lose. And in a הלכתית
halachic situation we would think about
חול המועד Chol HaMoed is a kind of time you take off
from work and other kinds of things where even if certain מלאכות
melachot are permitted but in a broader sense you have other responsibilities.
I don't know why that jumped into my head right now. Okay.
So תא שמע: Ta Shema: שני אחים שני שותפין האב ובנו הרב
ותלמידו פודין זה לזה מעשר שני. shnei achim shnei shutfin ha'av u'vno
ha'rav v'talmido podin ze la'ze ma'aser sheni. So now we have a
ברייתא. braita. There are two brothers together, or two business partners, or
a parent and a child, or a teacher and a student, פודין
זה לזה מעשר שני ומאכילין זה לזה מעשר עני. podin ze la'ze
ma'aser sheni u'machilin ze la'ze ma'aser ani. They can do the פדיון
מעשר שני pidyon ma'aser sheni and not just for themselves where they
have to add a חומש, chomesh, but they can even do it
for each other where they can avoid paying חומש chomesh because if
you're פודה podeh someone else's מעשר שני ma'aser sheni then there's no
חומש, chomesh, and they can eat each other's מעשר עני. ma'aser ani.
That is, you have to give מעשר עני ma'aser ani to someone
who's too poor. If you're in this kind of situation and you're
both reciprocally poor, so you give it to the other one and
then you get to eat it. Yes. Why would you think otherwise?
You might not have thought otherwise, and this is a תוספתא Tosefta
for מעשר שני, ma'aser sheni, it's an important הלכה halacha to be
aware of. I'm not sure what the הוה אמינא hava amina would
have been otherwise, but this is being brought in here in the
discussion of the חסרון כיס chesron kis issue.
That is, if someone, if your parents can be פודה podeh your
מעשר שני ma'aser sheni and things like that. So אי אמרת משל
בן, ei amrat mishel ben, if you're going to tell me that
the children have to pay for their parent, נמצא זה פורע חובו
משל עניים nimtza ze poreia chovo mishel aniyim because if you feed
your parents with מעשר עני, ma'aser ani, then you're stealing from עניים
aniyim in order to give it to your parents. Unless you're yourself
poor. Okay, unless you, unless they are poor. That is, if your
parents are poor enough that they should get מעשר עני ma'aser ani
anyway. But the assumption of this ברייתא braita at least is that
not. And therefore מעשר עני ma'aser ani is completely חולין chullin and
a poor person can do whatever he wants with it. Correct, but
it's פורע חובו משל עניים. poreia chovo mishel aniyim. That is, you
have a financial lien on your property as a child to provide
food for your parents. It's not just a nice thing. כיבוד אב
ואם kibbud av va'em is not just a nice thing, it's a
חוב, chov, it's a real technical legal obligation and therefore if you
owe your parents the money, the food to provide for them, and
you are taking מעשר עני ma'aser ani and feeding your parents with
it, you're פורע חובו בשל עניים. poreia chovo b'shel aniyim. Now how
much is that a rhetorical move, how much is that a הלכתית
halachic move is really a question of how to read all of
these סוגיות. sugyot. That is, these are the הלכות halachot of כיבוד
אב ואם, kibbud av va'em, but somehow to us they feel less
הלכתי halachic in a sense. It feels much more not tied down
in the same way, and that's why we have the רי"ף Rif
and the רמב"ם Rambam to solidify it. Okay. So פורע חובו משל
עניים poreia chovo mishel aniyim ולא צריכא להעדפה. v'la tzricha l'ha'adafa. No,
it was extra, it wasn't actually מעשר. ma'aser. הכי היינו דקתני עלה,
hachi haynu d'katani alah, אמר רבי יהודה, amar Rabbi Yehuda, תבא מאירה
למי שמאכיל את אביו מעשר עני. tavo me'eira l'mi she'ma'achil et aviv
ma'aser ani. And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said a person should be
cursed who feeds his father מעשר עני. ma'aser ani. ואי לאו העדפה
מאי נפקא מינה? v'i lav ha'adafa mai nafka mina? Why should there
be a נפקא מינה, nafka mina, I mean what's the difference if
you're feeding him the extra, not the actually the מעשר? ma'aser? Okay.
בראוי ליורשו. b'ra'uy l'yorsho. It must be to, sorry, I skipped a
line. מאי נפקא מינה, mai nafka mina, אפילו הכי זילא בי מילתא.
afilu hachi zeila bei milta. No, it's still not nice, it's still
not appropriate. That is, it may be technically permitted to feed your
parents מעשר עני ma'aser ani exactly like Charlie was saying, nonetheless the
fact is it's not appropriate
because you should be feeding them food that you buy or that
they buy or something. Okay. תא שמע, Ta Shema, שאלו את רבי
אליעזר, sha'alu et Rabbi Eliezer, עד היכן כיבוד אב ואם? ad heichan
kibbud av va'em? How far do you have to go for כיבוד
אב ואם? kibbud av va'em? אמר להם, amar lahem, כדי שיטול ארנקי,
k'dei she'yitol arnaki, ארנקי ויזרקנו לים בפניו ואינו מכלימו. arnaki v'yizrakenu l'yam
b'fanav v'eino machlimo. So he said it has to be to the
point where your parent takes your wallet from you and throws it
into the sea in front of you and you do not get
upset. Right, but he doesn't say you can't still sue for damages.
Ah, okay, so that's the other question. Meaning already we said if
the obligation is משל בן, mishel ben, then it would make sense
to a certain extent. That is, you owe the parent money.
Mom says look, I already have enough to eat, I'm going to
take your money and throw it in the sea. That is, the
money was mine. This was similar to the קידושין Kiddushin case we
had at twenty דף daf ago. Right, but if it was a
million dollars it's a little bit different. It is a little bit
different. I mean, conceptually it's not any different. No. The fact is
that emotionally it feels very different to have wasted one dollar than
a thousand dollars, but functionally it's the same. It's interesting, it goes
back to the סוגיא sugya about twenty דף daf ago where הרי
את מקודשת לי harei at mekudeshet li and וזרקתו לים, v'zarakto l'yam,
the woman takes the קידושין Kiddushin money and throws it into the
ocean. Does that mean she accepted it and was demonstrating her ownership
over it by throwing it away, or was it a way of
rejecting it? How do you get into how technically or how psychologically
or how realistically do you parse that situation?
Who is entitled to hire divers to go get the money and
if the money is retrieved, who owns it? Well, that's also a
good question and that asks a whole aspect of maritime law. For
sure. There was a great, great section in Cannery Row where in
prohibition there was the diver was hired to bring all of the
booze down to the bottom of the ocean and he would only
bring up one tenth of what he found and the rest he
would sell to the bars. Okay. So ואימא במשל אב ve-eima be-mishel
av if you're going to say that the requirement comes from the
parents' money, so מאי נפקא מינה? mai nafka mina? So ראוי ליורשו.
raui leyorsho. So because if the parent, meaning the test of כבוד
אב ואם Kibbud Av v'Em is that they won't get angry at
you, you don't get angry at them when they waste your money,
well that only makes sense if the obligation is parents' money, not
children's money. So the נפקא מינה nafka mina is ראוי ליורשו, raui
leyorsho, that is if you are one of the children who is
going to inherit from their parents' estate, that is if they waste
their own money, then you're going to be upset that they're wasting
their own money. And that's also a test of how angry you
get at them or not. Okay. וכי הא דרבה בר רב הונא
דרב הונא קרא שיראי דאנפי. ve-chi ha de-Rabbah bar Rav Huna de-Rav
Huna kara shirai de-anpai. So and and this is like the case
of
רבה בר רב הונא, Rabbah bar Rav Huna, that is רבה Rabbah
the son of רב הונא Rav Huna in front of רב הונא
Rav Huna his father, so he was already רב הונא Rav Huna
was very aged. קרא שיראי באנפי רבה בריה kara shirai be-anpai Rabbah
berei and he tore a very expensive silk in front of באנפי
be-anpai רבה Rabbah בריה, berei, in front of his son רבה. Rabbah.
ואמר איזיל אחזי אי רתח אי לא רתח. ve-amar eizil achezi i
ratach i lo ratach. I'm going to test whether he gets angry
or not. Okay. ודילמא רתח, ve-dilma ratach, so maybe he's going to
get angry? וקא עבר על לפני עור, ve-ka avar al lifnei iver,
that he's set up a situation where now רב הונא Rav Huna
will be עובר over on לפני עור lifnei iver because he's made
his son get angry at him. So you shouldn't set people up
in these kind of tricks, right? We also saw with the marital
case as well. Oh, I'm going to test whether he gets angry
or not. So somehow there are a lot of themes playing out
throughout the first פרק perek here that חוזר על עצמו chozer al
atzmo interestingly. Okay. אי רתח אי לא רתח ודילמא וקא עבר על
לפני עור לא תתן מכשול. i ratach i lo ratach ve-dilma ve-ka
avar al lifnei iver lo titein michshol. דמחיל ליה, de-machil lei,
maybe he must have already, he was already מוחל. mochel. Okay. ליקרייה
le-ikrei on itself. הא קא עבר משום בל תשחית. ha ka avar
mishum bal tashchit.
So he's still, he's destroying a shirt, a very nice silk shirt.
Okay. So that's בל תשחית, bal tashchit, you shouldn't just wantonly destroy
things for no reason. דעבד ליה בפומביוני. de-avad lei be-pumbeioni. He did
it in a place where it was in the tailor's shop. So
he's not going to cost him anything because they're going to fix
it up or it was on the edge of the shirt or
something. It was in a place where it wouldn't really damage the
value. It just, it looks very dramatic, but it's not actually going
to damage the shirt. ודילמא משום הכי לא רתח, ve-dilma mishum hachi
lo ratach, so maybe then he wouldn't get angry because he'll also
know that it was in the place where it's not going to
damage the shirt. דעבד ליה בשעת רתיחיה. de-avad lei be-sha'at retichei. He
did it when he was already in an angry, prone to being
angry. This is a very strange story. What's happening? רב הונא Rav
Huna is testing his son רבה Rabbah whether or not he's going
to get angry in a time when he's already starting to get
angry. He's trying to egg him on to test his כבוד אב
ואם. Kibbud Av v'Em. It seems very strange.
And there are a lot of הלכה halakha obstacles to what רב
הונא Rav Huna did, that is בל תשחית bal tashchit don't destroy
the shirt, לפני עור lifnei iver don't set up a situation where
where your son is going to sin. So to a certain extent,
it makes sense to read this as רב הונא Rav Huna not
thinking rationally. רב הונא Rav Huna is just doing whatever. But the
גמרא Gemara is now trying to explain or justify רב הונא's Rav
Huna's actions in a in a seemingly very contrived way. So off
a father tears a shirt on שבת. Shabbat.
I mean, isn't that... I mean, that's being מחלל שבת. mechallel Shabbat.
That's since not an ordinary... It's a separate question for now. The
גמרא Gemara in שבת Shabbat talks extensively about קורע על מתו koreia
al meto and what kind of emotional release comes from tearing a
garment to a certain extent is sometimes constructive, so you would be
חייב chayav but other cases it's מקלקל mekalkel so you wouldn't be
חייב chayav and it's
מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה, melacha she-eina tzricha le-gufa, it's a long סוגיא
sugya there in קל-ish Kuf-Lamed in שבת, Shabbat, something like that. I'm
getting the דף daf wrong. Okay. בעי ליה לרבי יחזקאל לרמי בריה.
be'i lei le-Rabbi Yechezkel le-Rami berei. הנשרפין בנסקלין. ha-nisrafin ba-niskalin. What happens
if נשרפין, nisrafin, people who are חייב שריפה, chayav sreifah, get mixed
up among the criminals who are נסקלין, niskalin, who are going to
be stoned? So this was from רבי יחזקאל Rabbi Yechezkel asked רמי
Rami his son. Okay. רבי שמעון אומר ידוני בסקילה שהשריפה חמורה. Rabbi
Shimon omer yadunu bi-skilah she-ha-sreifah chamurah. So he says everybody should get
סקילה skilah because שריפה sreifah is a more extreme punishment. And therefore,
and that's רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon's opinion, again there's a big מחלוקת
machlokes in סנהדרין Sanhedrin which of the different ארבע מיתות arba mitot
is the worst. So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon thinks that שריפה sreifah
is worse than סקילה skilah and therefore they should all get סקילה
skilah because you should give them, in a case of ספק, safek,
give them the less severe punishment. Now of course it's interesting to
think, if the תורה Torah prescribes that these people have to get
שריפה sreifah and not סקילה, skilah, you might think we have no
right to execute them in any way at all. If we're not
going to give them שריפה, sreifah, if they're all mixed up, then
everyone of these criminals now is a ספק. safek. But that's sort
of not how רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon addresses it. So anyway, שהשריפה
חמורה. she-ha-sreifah chamurah. אמר ליה רב יהודה בריה אבא לאו תניא הכי.
amar lei Rav Yehudah berei abba lav tanya hachi. אבא, Abba, don't
teach like this. מאי איריא שריפה חמורה תיפוק ליה דרובא נסקלין. mai
irya sreifah chamurah tipok lei de-ruba niskalin. You shouldn't say that it's
because שריפה sreifah is more severe, you should say that it's because
the majority of the people there are... of סקילה. sekila. In other
words, don't say that you're doing a less severe punishment, just say
בטל ברוב. battul berov. So and he told his father the important
part, he said, אבא לא תתניא, Abba lo titnaya, don't לא תתניא
הכי, lo titnaya hachi, don't teach like this. He says, אלא הכי
תניא, ela hachi tanya, this is how you should teach it: הנסקלין
בנשרפין. haniskalin banisrafin. If people who were going to be stoned were
mixed among the רוב rov of people who were going to be
נשרפין. nisrafin. So אמר ליה, Amar lei, אי הכי, ei hachi, אימא
סיפא, eima seifa, you should teach the end of the משנה, mishna,
וחכמים אומרים ידוני בשריפה. vachachamim omrim yidonu bisreifa. So the חכמים chachamim's
opinion say you should do שריפה sreifa שהסקילה חמורה shehasekila chamura because
they disagree with Rabbi Shimon about which punishment is worse, and they
think that סקילה sekila is worse than שריפה. sreifa. So מאי איריא
דסקילה חמורה, mai irya disekila chamura, why does it why should we
learn that סקילה sekila is worse? So תיפוק ליה דרובא בנשרפין. teipok
lei deruba banisrafin. So he pushed back against his son, he said,
look, but the סיפא seifa said it's not because of of who's
the רוב, rov, it goes by which is more severe. So אמר
ליה התם רבנן הוא דקאמרי ליה לרבי שמעון דקאמר שריפה חמורה, amar
lei hatam rabanan hu deka'amri lei leRabbi Shimon deka'amar sreifa chamura, because
Rabbi Shimon is the one who says שריפה חמורה. sreifa chamura. לא,
סקילה חמורה, lo, sekila chamura, and חכמים chachamim are trying to force
their opinion on Rabbi Shimon to convince him that סקילה sekila is
more חמור chamur by teaching the סיפא. seifa. That is, the רישא
reisha of that משנה mishna is from Rabbi Shimon and the סיפא
seifa is חכמים chachamim responding to him. The whole point of this
discussion here about מיתת בית דין misas beis din is brought in
about where it's a מחלוקת machlokes between father and son that maybe
was not the most deferential. That is, he said, oh, אבא לא
תתניא הכי, Abba lo titnaya hachi, don't teach it like this. So
he says, אלא הכי תניא, ela hachi tanya, you should teach it
like this. So אמר ליה שמואל לרב יהודה שיננא. Amar lei Shmuel
leRav Yehuda Shinena. So שמואל Shmuel said to רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda,
שיננא. Shinena. Now, שיננא Shinena is a nickname that's unclear what it
means. Either it's from שינון shinun like learning, you're very learned, or
שיננא Shinena it means you show your teeth a lot. Either he
had sharp teeth or he smiled a lot or or some kind
of sarcastic he's very sharp it's unclear. So he says, שיננא לא
תימא ליה לאבוך הכי, Shinena lo teima lei le'avuch hachi, you shouldn't
speak to your father this
way, דתניא הרי שהיה אביו עובר על דברי תורה, detanya harei shehaya
aviv over al divrei torah, if you see your father violating some
עבירה, aveira, אל יאמר לו אבא עברת על דברי תורה, al yomar
lo Abba avarta al divrei torah, don't tell him, father, you are
violating the words of the תורה, Torah, אלא אומר לו אבא כך
כתוב בתורה. ela omer lo Abba kach katuv batorah. כך כתוב בתורה
Kach katuv batorah תורי קא מצער ליה? torei ka metza'er lei? So
you should tell him it's written like this in the תורה. Torah.
Like you see your father wearing שעטנז, shatnez, you don't say, father,
you're violating שעטנז. shatnez. You say, doesn't it say in the תורה
Torah לא תלבש שעטנז? lo tilbash shatnez? That's more of a deferential
way of of saying the same thing. Ah, but he said, but
wait, if you're going to say כך כתוב בתורה, kach katuv batorah,
isn't that going to cause him צער? tza'ar? אלא אומר לו אבא
מקרא כתוב בתורה כך. ela omer lo Abba mikra katuv batorah kach.
Don't even say this is written in the תורה, Torah, say, there's
a פסוק pasuk that says לא תלבש שעטנז. lo tilbash shatnez. Okay.
But there are a lot of things that are considered דאורייתא de'oraisa
that are not explicit in the תורה. Torah. That's also דאורייתא? de'oraisa?
Well,
let's pause for a moment and consider. The רמב"ם Rambam's שיטה shita
is very important here, which is that many of the things that
we call quote דאורייתא de'oraisa and which their halachic weight is what
we would call דאורייתא, de'oraisa, the רמב"ם Rambam calls not דאורייתא, de'oraisa,
not מן התורה, min hatorah, but he calls דברי סופרים. divrei sofrim.
Because the רמב"ם Rambam thinks, the רמב"ם Rambam in ספר המצוות Sefer
Hamitzvos is very clear and the פירוש המשנה, Peirush Hamishna, that things
which are explicit in the תורה, Torah, that's what is מן התורה,
min hatorah, and things which are not explicit in the תורה, Torah,
which are learned out from דרשות drashos and things like that, are
much more they're sort of the next step down. They're not what
we would call דרבנן, derabanan, they're somehow a middle category. The weight
is what we would call דאורייתא de'oraisa weight, but it's not explicit
in the תורה. Torah. And there are many נפקא מינה nafka minas
and we saw even a few days ago the question of, oh,
it's מדרש חכמים midrash chachamim who. So fine, that's a מדרש חכמים,
midrash chachamim, that's what we would call a דאורייתא, de'oraisa, but because
it's learned from a מדרש, midrash, it's less than an explicit פסוק.
pasuk.
That's a big צריכא עיון. tzricha iyun. Okay.
So אלעזר בן מתיא אומר אבא אומר השקיני מים ומצוה לעשות. Elazar
ben Masya omer Abba omer hashkini mayim u'mitzvah la'asos. What if my
father asked me for a glass of water and I have a
מצוה mitzvah to go do? I have to go to שול, shul,
I have to go do ביקור חולים, bikur cholim, I have to,
I don't know, some other מצוה. mitzvah. So
מניח אני כבוד אבא ועושה את המצוה, maniach ani kavod Abba ve'oseh
es hamitzvah, so should I not neglect the כבוד kavod for my
father and go do the מצוה? mitzvah? שאני ואבא חייבים במצוה, she'ani
ve'abba chayavim bemitzvah,
because my father and myself are both obligated in the same מצוה.
mitzvah. That is, I don't know, I try to think of a
good example, but there's something going on in the street and I
need to go, you know, raise money for פדיון שבויים pidyon shvuyim
or something. Again, it depends on the kind of מצוה mitzvah also,
right?
A מצוה עוברת mitzvah overes is going to be very different way
of relating to this than a מצוה שאינה עוברת. mitzvah she'eina overes.
Like okay, if I can wait two minutes and then go do
the מצוה, mitzvah, obviously I should pour the glass of water and
then just go and do the מצוה. mitzvah. So it's kind of
a strange question, but the point is that I and my parent
are both obligated to do this מצוה mitzvah equally and therefore I
should leave aside כבוד אב kavod av in order to go do
the מצוה. mitzvah. So איסי בן יהודה אומר אם אפשר למצוה ליעשות
על ידי אחרים, Issi ben Yehuda omer im efshar lemitzvah le'asos al
yedei acherim, if other people can do the מצוה, mitzvah, תיעשה על
ידי אחרים, te'aseh al yedei acherim, then let other people do it,
וילכו בכיבוד אב, vayeilechu bechibud av, and you should do כיבוד אב.
kibbud av. That is... Nobody else is going to do this מצוה
mitzvah for you, right? Your parent asked you to do something, there's
no one else who's going to do that, you have to do
that. So the fact is if the other מצוה mitzvah is a
מצוה mitzvah that's נעשית על ידי אחרים, naaseit al yedei acherim, then,
and that category, distinguishing between מצוה אפשר ליעשות על ידי אחרים, mitzvah
efshar l'easot al yedei acherim, it could be done by someone else,
and מצוה mitzvah that only you can do, comes up in a
lot of contexts. I remember hearing when I was in ישיבה yeshiva
in Israel, there was someone who wanted to go volunteer for מגן
דוד אדום Magen David Adom while they were in ישיבה, yeshiva, and
there was a big halachic discussion in the חרד״ל Chardal community about
how to, really the opinion to not allow that, because look, if
you're a ישיבה yeshiva student, fine, there are other people who are
ambulance drivers, there are other people who are EMTs, and that's a
מצוה אפשר ליעשות על ידי אחרים. mitzvah efshar l'easot al yedei acherim.
Now other communities may take a different approach to that, but it's
important to consider that there are people who have certain responsibilities and
other responsibilities and you're in a different context. By that argument, ישיבה
yeshiva students shouldn't be serving in the army. It's a major question,
and we have explicit ברייתות beraitot that talk about ישיבה yeshiva students
going to serve in the army when it's necessary. So there's much
more to talk about, about those kinds of things, but it's really,
you always see חז״ל Chazal navigating the tension between different responsibilities and
you know, there are only 28 hours in a day.
So there's a lot of life to squeeze into a short time,
and that's exactly the difficulty here. Okay, so אמר רב מתנא הלכה
כאיסי בן יהודה. Amar Rav Matna halacha k'Isi ben Yehuda. So רב
מתנא Rav Matna finally says, he responds to איסי בן יהודה, Isi
ben Yehuda, he says the הלכה halacha is like איסי בן יהודה.
Isi ben Yehuda. That is, if it's מצוה אפשר ליעשות על ידי
אחרים, mitzvah efshar l'easot al yedei acherim, other people can go do
this מצוה, mitzvah, then you have to take care of כיבוד אב
ואם. kibbud av v'eim. And you can think of many examples. Now
there are many מצוות mitzvot that you have to do yourself, מצוה
שבגופו mitzvah shebegufu or מצוה mitzvah that you have a specific חיוב.
chiyuv. You have to go hear the מגילה Megillah reading, you have
to go light your חנוכה Chanukah candles. Those are מצוות mitzvot that
other people probably can't—חנוכה Chanukah candles maybe somebody else could do for
you—but מגילה Megillah reading nobody else can do that for you, you
have to go and hear the מגילה. Megillah. So that would override
כיבוד אב ואם. kibbud av v'eim. ואמר רב יצחק בר שילא אמר
רב מתנא אמר רב חסדא האב שמחל על כבודו כבודו מחול. V'amar
Rav Yitzchak bar Shila amar Rav Matna amar Rav Chisda ha-av shemachal
al kevodo kevodo machul. If a parent is מוחל mochel on their
כבוד, kavod, they forgive on their honor, they cancel out their honor,
then their honor is forgiven, their honor is negated. So you can
imagine whatever was כבוד. kavod. כבוד kavod was מאכילו משקהו מלביש ומכסה
מכניס ומוציא. maachilo mashkehu malbish u-mechase machnis u-motzi. If a parent tells
you, "I don't need you to buy my food for me anymore."
Now again, it's משל אב mishel av anyway, they're buying it with
their own money, but they need someone to do their errands. If
the parent says, "Look, I'm okay this week, you don't need to
go do it for me," then כבודו מחול, kevodo machul, you don't
have to insist on כבוד kavod anyway if the parent forgives it.
הרב שמחל על כבודו אין כבודו מחול. Harav shemachal al kevodo ein
kevodo machul. But if your teacher cancels their honor, then that honor
is not forgiven. That is, the relationship you have with your teacher
is of a higher level or more severe necessity of כבוד. kavod.
Again, because of the ברייתא beraita says אין כבוד אלא תורה ein
kavod ela Torah and you have to show כבוד kavod to anyone
who teaches you תורה. Torah. It's more objective about your relationship with
תורה Torah and with God in a different way than your relationship
with your parents. It might also be like a politeness factor too,
in that like parents tend to be more comfortable telling you, "Yes,
I need you to do this for me." Maybe, in our society
for sure, in חז״ל Chazal society I'm not sure. You know, they
were a very rigidly hierarchical, deferential society for their parents and their
elders in a way that we've lost. So I don't know, it's
a very good question to think about. Okay, ורב יוסף אמר אפילו
הרב שמחל על כבודו כבודו מחול. V'Rav Yosef amar afilu ha-rav shemachal
al kevodo kevodo machul. And רב יוסף Rav Yosef says even a
teacher who's מוחל mochel on their כבוד, kavod, שנאמר וה׳ הולך לפניהם
יומם. she-ne'emar v'Adonai holech lifneihem yomam. God walked in front of them
during the day. That what, God was going to lead the whole
מחנה ישראל machaneh Yisrael with a whole big thing, you know, that
was like שלעפינג schlepping in the desert. So obviously as if God
was מוחל mochel on God's own כבוד kavod in that situation, and
therefore we can learn that extension. Again, it's one of the many
places where the relationship with someone who teaches you תורה Torah and
from God are analogies, right?
לרבות תלמידי חכמים L'rabot talmidei chachamim and things like that רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva coming up. Okay, so וה׳ הולך לפניהם יומם. V'Adonai holech
lifneihem yomam. אמר רבא היכי השתא התם הקדוש ברוך הוא עלמא דיליה.
Amar Rava heichi hashta hatam Hakadosh Baruch Hu alma dilei. It's God's
world, ותורה דיליה, v'Torah dilei, and the תורה Torah is God's תורה.
Torah.
So מחיל ליקרא. machil likra. הכא תורה דיליה היא? Hacha Torah dilei
hi? But in this case, right, so what's going on? It's תורה
דיליה. Torah dilei. Is כבוד kavod is תלוי בתורה, talui ba-Torah, right?
Meaning in one case you're talking about God being מוחל mochel on
God's own כבוד. kavod. But in another case, the רב Rav is
being מוחל mochel not on the רב's Rav own כבוד, kavod, it's
on כבוד התורה. kevod ha-Torah. That is, the only reason you show
כבוד kavod to your teacher is because you're showing כבוד kavod for
the תורה. Torah. It's not actually about the person. And therefore they
don't have a right, a רב Rav doesn't have a right to
be מוחל mochel on his or her own כבוד kavod in the
sense that a teacher can't be מוחל mochel their כבוד kavod because
their כבוד kavod is a stand-in for the כבוד התורה kevod ha-Torah
in a way that a teacher to their student represents the chain
of transmission, represents the whole notion of... תורה שבעל פה, Torah she-ba'al
peh, it's a very different notion than just treating this person with
respect. It's actually about the whole process of learning תורה. Torah. Okay.
So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, אין תורה דיליה. ein Torah diley. No.
So he says אין תורה דיליה, ein Torah diley, no the תורה
Torah is his his own תורה. Torah. That is the teacher's תורה.
Torah. That is the honor you show for the teacher is not
because of the person but actually is because of the תורה Torah
but it's the תורה Torah their own תורה. Torah. דכתיב ובתורתו יהגה
יומם ולילה. Dechtiv u'veTorato yehgeh yomam valailah.
You are engrossed in his תורה Torah day and night but it's
תורתו, Torato, his own תורה Torah as if. That is a person
who's a teacher has actually acquired that תורה Torah for themselves. It's
not about showing כבוד kavod for somehow someone else's תורה, Torah, God's
תורה. Torah. The תורה Torah that you're showing כבוד kavod for actually
is the תורה Torah that they acquire for themselves and therefore you
really are showing כבוד kavod for the person and therefore the person
would have the right to be מוחל mochel on their כבוד. kavod.
Okay. איני והאמר רבא אשקי בהילולא דבריה. Iny ve'ha'amar Rava ashki behilula
de'brei.
So רבא Rava went to it was at his son's wedding and
he was drinking a glass of wine ודלי כסא לרב פפא ולרב
הונא בריה דרבי יהושע vedali kasa l'Rav Papa u'l'Rav Huna brei d'Rabbi
Yehoshua וקמו מקמיה דרב מרי ולרב פנחס בריה דרב חסדא vekama mikamei
d'Rav Mari u'l'Rav Pinchas brei d'Rav Chisda ולא קמו מקמיה. velo kama
mikamei. So
and they came before these other rabbis and they didn't stand up
for them. So איקפד, ikbad, they got upset ואמר הני רבנן רבנן
והני רבנן לאו רבנן ve'amar hani rabanan rabanan vehani rabanan lav rabanan
and some of the people said, those rabbis, those are really rabbis
and those rabbis, they're not really rabbis. ותו רב פפא הוה משקי
בהילולא דאבא מר בריה. V'tu Rav Papa havi mashki behilula de'Abba Mar
brei. So then and רב פפא Rav Papa was at the wedding
of אבא מר בריה Abba Mar brei so אבא מר Abba Mar
that is presumably פפא בר פפא Papa bar Papa is a אבו
מרי בר פפא Abu Mari bar Papa that we know from the
סיום. Siyum. So it's his name was probably פפא, Papa, פפא בר
פפא Papa bar Papa that's why he's אבא מר בריה. Abba Mar
brei. So he's at his son's
wedding ודלי ליה כסא ליצחק בריה ולרב יהודה vedali lei kasa l'Yitzchak
brei u'l'Rav Yehuda ולא קם מקמיה velo kam mikamei and he didn't
stand up for them. ואיקפד, V'ikbid, אפילו הכי הידור עבדי. afilu hachi
hidar mavdey. But he still he did a הידור. hidur. הידור Hidur
is like where you kind of like sort of get up but
you don't like really get up. Okay. I think this is a
good place to stop.